Indiana University Libraries Government Publications Department records, 1942-2005 C437
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University Libraries Government Publications Department records
1942-2005
1980-1996
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University, Bloomington. Libraries. Government Publications Department
C437
2.8 cubic feet 4 boxes
Since its inception, the Government Publications Department (GPD) at Indiana University has aimed to offer free access of government publications and other information to the general public. The GPD, now known as Government Information and Kent Cooper Services, houses records from city, county, state and federal governments, as well as many publications from foreign governments and international organizations. The collection consists of correspondence, reports, statistics, policy changes, and other information regarding GPD administration.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice required.
Administrative History
The Government Publications Department (GPD) at Indiana University, now known as Government Information and Kent Cooper Services, has always aimed to make government information and publications free and readily accessible to the public. Under its past and current titles, the GPD's responsibilities have been and still are to select, acquire and make available publications from city, county, state and federal governments. Additionally, the GPD has always maintained a selection of publications from foreign governments and international organizations.
At one point the GPD took part in the Documents Expediting Project (DOCEX), which was started by the Library of Congress in 1946. DOCEX was a unique program in that it provided a way to obtain documents that had previously been confidential or otherwise unattainable for the public, such as records relating to the U.S. involvement in World War II. While DOCEX was discontinued in 2004, the GPD continues to obtain government publications through the Federal Depository Library Program (FDLP), as well as the U.S. Government Printing Office (GPO).
Arrangement
The collection is organized into three series: U.S. government agencies, Administrative files and Subject files.
Scope and Content Note
The collection spans four boxes of records from GPD organized into three main series, based on the original order of the records as received by the Archives: U.S. Government Agencies, Administrative files, and Subject files.
The U.S. Government Agencies series contains twelve folders with documents spanning 1942 to 2004. The majority of these files are correspondence files between the GPD and various government agencies, such as the U.S. Army Department, U.S. Education Department, and the Foreign Broadcast Information Service, to name a few. Most of the correspondence between the GPD and these various government agencies is in regards to implementing or discontinuing certain programs such as DOCEX, as well as requesting specific documents or choosing from among lists of available publications.
The Administrative files series is made up of thirty-two folders ranging from the years 1944 to 1997. Most folders in this series pertain to policies, procedures, the implementation and maintenance of new systems, or financial reports. There are five folders from 1968 to 1974 that include reports, data and instructions for the Indiana Libraries Serials Data Bank (ILSDB) project, which was a collaborative project between participating Indiana libraries to compile an updated and comprehensive list of their serials. Also of interest in this series is the file IU Library, GPD Correspondence, 1944-1996 which contains correspondence between the GPD and other IU departments. Among these are mostly requests for documents, but there are also quite a few letters of thanks and praise which highlight several exceptional members of the GPD staff during the 1970s, 80s and 90s.
With eighty-five folders, the Subject files series is the largest of the three, and it takes up the entirety of Boxes 2, 3, and 4. The Subject series contains documents ranging from 1958 to 2005 and there is a diverse range of topics included in this section. From the 1990 guidelines for Americans with Disabilities to information about the Dean Candidates of 1996, the Subject files also contain many GPD statistics and information about the GPD in its early years.
Acquisition Information
Accession Information: 2011/025
Provenance
This collection was transferred to the University Archives from Government Information and Kent Cooper Services in March of 2011.
Appraisal
Some blank statistics forms and several documents unrelated to the collection were pulled from several of the files.
Depository libraries --Indiana --Bloomington.; Academic libraries --Departmental libraries --Indiana --Bloomington.; Indiana University. Libraries. Government Publications Department; Indiana University, Bloomington. Libraries. Government Publications Department -- Archives; Indiana University, Bloomington. Libraries. Government Publications Department -- Records and correspondence; Indiana University. Libraries. Government Publications Department -- Archives; Indiana University. Libraries. Government Publications Department -- Records and correspondence
- U.S. Government Agencies, 1942-2004 (Box 1)
  - US Correspondence File, 1946-2004 (Box 1)
    - Documents Expediting Service, 1947-2004 (Box 1)
    - Army Dept. Military Histories Office, Unit Histories of World War II, 1946-1975 (Box 1)
    - US Education Dept., 1985 (Box 1)
    - Depository Libraries‑ Indiana, 1957-1988 (Box 1)
    - Disposal Lists, 1976-1990 (Box 1)
    - Foreign Broadcast Info. Service, 1974-1993 (Box 1)
    - Map Deposit, 1981-1984 (Box 1)
    - US Army, 1980-1995 (Box 1)
    - US Defense Documentation Center, 1966-1983 (Box 1)
    - US Geological Survey, 1968-1992 (Box 1)
  - US Government Printing Office Correspondence, 1942‑1994 (Box 1)
  - Office of Management and Budget/ Federal Register, 1985-1989 (Box 1)
- Administrative files, 1944-1997 (Box 1)
  - IU Library GPD Correspondence, 1944-1996 (Box 1)
  - IU Library Cataloging Procedures and Policies, 1969-1978 (Box 1)
  - Indiana Libraries Serials Databank (ILSDB), 1968-1974 (Box 1)
    - Instructions, 1968-1971 (Box 1)
    - Financial Reports, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Expenditures for GPD Personnel and Titles Reported to Purdue, 1968-1971 (Box 1)
    - News Bulletin, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, Progress Reports, etc, 1969-1972 (Box 1)
  - Cataloging Statistics GPD, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Retrospective Conversion, 1993-1996 (Box 1)
  - Retro Coned Docs, 1993-1996 (Box 1)
  - Computer-Based Resources and Services Team, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Association of Research Libraries Task Force, Electronic Distribution of Documents, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Budget, 1990-1996 (Box 1)
  - CIC Interlibrary Loan Policy, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Database Selection Committee, 1993-1996 (Box 1)
  - GPD Equipment Requests, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - Documents Survey, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - Forms, 1983-1986 (Box 1)
    - Periodical Project, 1964-1969 (Box 1)
  - Fax Policy, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Family Leave Report, 1993-1996 (Box 1)
  - Filing Rules, 1981-1985 (Box 1)
  - Fund Managers Mtg, 1991-1996 (Box 1)
  - Gift Policy and Disposal of Materials, 1992 (Box 1)
  - GPD Stack Space and Shelving and Repair and Renovation, 1980-1992 (Box 1)
  - GPD/UGL ‑5th Floor, 1980-1982 (Box 1)
  - IU Admin Philosophy and the Strategic Directions Charter and the Strategic Directions Initiative, 1990-1996 (Box 1)
  - Library Guides Docs, 1987-1995 (Box 1)
  - Online Computer Library Center Inc. History, 1989 (Box 1)
  - Postage Reimbursement US File, 1997 (Box 1)
  - Processing Government Docs for GPD, 1997 (Box 1)
  - SUDOC Sort (From GPD), 1990 (Box 1)
- Subject files, 1958-2005 (Box 2)
  - African Studies, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Americans with Disabilities Guidelines, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Bloomington Delivery Service Handbook, 1984-1991 (Box 2)
  - Bob Knight Library Endowment, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Branch Libraries, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Branch Review, 1999-2008 (Box 2)
  - Business/SPEA Review, 2004-2005 (Box 2)
  - Communication Task Force, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Coalition for Networked Info, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence between Marian Shaaban, Gwendolen Carter and Louise Holborn, 1975-1976 (Box 2)
  - Dean Candidates, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Department of Economics, 1987-1992 (Box 2)
  - Depository Library Costs Survey, 1989-1996 (Box 2)
  - Farmington Plan Survey, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Geography and Map Library (GML), 1958-1989 (Box 2)
    - Collection Development, 1984 (Box 2)
    - Floor Plans, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Handbook, undated (Box 2)
    - Monthly Reports, 1979-1991 (Box 2)
    - New GML Library, 1988-1991 (Box 2)
    - Planning, 1987-1991 (Box 2)
    - Space, 1967-1991 (Box 2)
  - Globalization Report, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Gov't Printing Office Budget Crisis, 1992-1994 (Box 2)
  - IO-Government Documents Task Force, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - IU Aerospace Research Applications Center, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
  - IU Library- Slavic Collection, 1962-1965 (Box 2)
  - Indiana Networking for Documents and Info of Gov't Organizations (INDIGO) – Bylaws, undated (Box 2)
  - Indiana Public Records Law. (Confidentiality of Library Circucation Records), 1988-1995 (Box 2)
  - Indiana State Library Regional Depository Lists, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
  - Indiana State Library – Sunset Committee and Networking and Automation Plans, 1989-1992 (Box 2)
  - Indiana University – General, 1995-1996 (Box 2)
  - IUB Libraries Plans, Mission, etc., 1991-1995 (Box 2)
    - Reference/Graduate Assistant and Work Study Student Orientation, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Supervisor's Handbook, 2006 (Box 2)
  - International Book Subject Guide, 1992 (Box 2)
  - Kirkwood Hall Remodeling, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Laboratories, National (Locations), 1995 (Box 2)
  - IU Library Guides, 1992-1994 (Box 2)
  - Library of Congress in 21st Century, 1997 (Box 2)
  - Limestone Tower, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Lockhart, Oliver C. Gift Collection China, Bolivia, Ecuador, Chile, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Man and His Environment, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Materials Budget, 1976-1997 (Box 2)
  - Materials Requests, 1981-1993 (Box 2)
    - 1994-1997 (Box 2)
  - Newspapers and Serials, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Oath of Office, Indiana/Local, 1995 (Box 2)
  - Online Computer Library Center (OCLC) Terminal, 1991-1993 (Box 2)
  - Preservation Copying, 1992-1994 (Box 2)
  - Privacy Task Force Report, 2001-2005 (Box 2)
  - Prof. Nicholas DeWitt, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Public Law 480, 1958-1968; 1968 (Box 2)
  - Public Services Cluster, 1991-1994 (Box 2)
  - Reference Services and Computers, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Reorganization Plan 1992‑1994 (Box 2)
  - Research Collections and Services Department, 1992-1994 (Box 3)
  - Serials, 1980-1990 (Box 3)
  - Sexual Harassment, 1990-1994 (Box 3)
  - Standard Industrial Classification (SIC) Replacement- North Amer. Industry Classification System (NAICS), 1994-1996 (Box 3)
  - Strengths- Weaknesses- Opportunities- Threats (SWOT), 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - State Plan for Depository Libraries, 1982-1992 (Box 3)
  - Student Building, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Floorplans, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - Tech Link, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Technical Services Review, 1989-1993 (Box 3)
  - Telephones and Data Jacks, 1988-1995 (Box 3)
  - Title II‑C on Environment, 1992-1993 (Box 3)
  - Transfer and Withdraw Policy, 1991-1994 (Box 3)
  - Union – CWA, 1994 (Box 3)
  - US Book Exchange Inc, 1967-1970 (Box 3)
  - United States Geological Survey Depository Program, 1970-1982 (Box 3)
  - Western European Programs, 1966 (Box 3)
  - Withdrawal and Retention Policy, 1999-2002 (Box 3)
  - Ann. Report (GPD), 1990-1994 (Box 3)
  - GPD – Annual Statistics Report, 1988-1996 (Box 3)
  - GPD Statistics, 1999-2002 (Box 4)
  - Annual Reports – Microforms, 1975-1991 (Box 4)
  - Book Count, 1945-1980; 1980 (Box 4)
  - IU Library Statistics, 1992-2004 (Box 4)
  - Statistics: US File 1966-1997 (2 files) (Box 4)
  - GPD Statistics- NATC, 1997 (Box 4)
  - GPD/ARL Stats, 2000-2004 (Box 4)
  - Government Info, Microforms and Statistical Services Annual Reports, 2003-2005 (Box 4)